A Guide to the Lewis Family Papers, 1776-1841
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Lewis Family Papers, 1776-1841
Library of Virginia
20902
71 leaves
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by Dr. Meriwether Lewis Anderson, Richmond, Virginia, 15 February 1935.
Biographical Information
William Lewis (1733-1781) and Lucy Meriwether (1752-1837) married in 1768 or 1769 and lived in Albemarle County, Virginia. They had three children: Jane Meriwether Lewis (1770-1845), Meriwether Lewis (1774- 1809), and Reuben Lewis (1777-1844). Jane Meriwether Lewis married Edmund Anderson (1763-1810), and they had nine children. Meriwether Lewis served in the United States Army and as private secretary to President Thomas Jefferson (1743-1826). He led the Lewis and Clark Expedition to explore the Louisiana Purchase and was appointed governor of the Louisiana Territory. Reuben Lewis served as an indian agent for the United States government. Lucy Meriwether Lewis remarried, marrying John Marks (d. 1791). They had two children: John Hastings Marks (b. 1785) and Mary Garland Marks (b. 1788).
Scope and Content
Papers, 1776-1841, of the Lewis family of Albemarle County, Virginia, and Georgia, consisting of advertisements, deeds, letters, lists, and transcripts. Correspondence consists mostly of letters from Meriwether Lewis (1774-1809) to his mother Lucy Meriwether Lewis Marks (1752-1837) discussing his education, and his his service in the United States army during and after the Whiskey Rebellion. Lewis also discusses personal and family business including his efforts to settle land claims in Kentucky, his concerns over the education of Reuben Lewis (1777-1844) and John Hastings Marks (b. ca. 1785), and news on his sister's family. Also includes correspondence concerning the Lewis and Clark Expedition, including a description of geography, animal life, and plants; and concerning his appointment as governor of the Louisiana Territory. Also includes correspondence of Reuben Lewis relating to his role as an indian agent in the Louisiana and Arkansas Territories. Papers also include a deed for land in Culpeper County, Virginia, from Thomas, Lord Fairfax (1693-1781) to John Francis Lucas Jacoby; a commission for John Marks (d. 1791) as a captain in the Continental Army; papers regarding the transfer of a land warrant from Reuben Lewis to William Moore of Alabama; a letter from Thomas Walker Gilmer (1802-1844) and others to Lucy Marks concerning their hopes to prepare a biography of Meriwether Lewis; a letter from William Meriwether to Reuben Lewis containing transcripts of a letter from William Lewis to his wife and a receipt for rations; an advertisement for John Hudson and Company; and a list of land warrant entries.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically
Item List
- Deed, 4 July 1777, for 341 acres in Culpeper County, Virginia, from Thomas, Lord Fairfax, to John Francis Lucas Jacoby., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Commission, 20 March 1779, for John Marks as captain in the 13th Virginia Regiment, Continental Army, signed by John Jay., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Letter, 7 March [1787?], from Meriwether Lewis [Albemarle County, Virginia] to Reuben Lewis, Wilkes County, Georgia, stating that he is unable to visit because of school plans and other matters., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, [ca. 1787-1792], from Meriwether Lewis at Cloverfields [Albemarle County, Virginia], to his mother Lucy [Meriwether Lewis] Marks, [Wilkes County,] Georgia, containing news about his sister's family living in Hanover County, Virginia, his education and personal news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 12 May 1789, from Meriwether Lewis to Lucy Marks, Wilk[e]s County, Georgia, containing family and personal news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 16 October 1791, from Meriwether Lewis, Cloverfields, [Albemarle County, Virginia], to Lucy Marks, Wilk[e]s County, Georgia, discussing William Lewis' estate, his sister's family, and personal news., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 19 April 1792, from Meriwether Lewis to Lucy Marks regarding his sister's family and personal news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 4 October 1794, from Meriwether Lewis, Winchester, [Virginia], to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, discussing his military service and preparations to march to western Pennsylvania to put down the Whiskey Rebellion., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 13 October [1794], from Meriwether Lewis, Winchester, to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, concerning his military service and the participants in the Whiskey Rebellion., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 24 November 1794, from Meriwether Lewis, McFarlin's Farm, Pennsylvania, to Lucy Marks, [Albemarle County], concerning camp life and the Whiskey Rebellion., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 7 December 1794, from Meriwether Lewis to Lucy Marks, Locust Hill, [Albemarle County], detailing plans to visit Kentucky when his service is done and his need for money., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 24 December 1794, from Meriwether Lewis, McFarlin's Farm, to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, describing conditions of his camp., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 6 April 1795, from Meriwether Lewis, McFarling's [McFarlin's Farm], to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, concerning camp life and discussing family news., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 22 May 1795, from Meriwether Lewis, Pittsburg[h], [Pennsylvania], to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, concerning family and personal matters., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 23 November 1795, from Meriwether Lewis, Greenville [?], to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, regarding family and personal matters, and how the army has given him experience., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 2 May 1797, from Meriwether Lewis, Charlottesville, [Virginia], to Nicholas Johnson, Wilk[e]s County, Georgia, regarding the settlement of his and his mother's affairs and the estate of John Marks, and commenting on Kentucky lands., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 14 June 1797, from Meriwether Lewis, at Colonel Crocket's, [Kentucky], to Lucy Marks, [Albemarle County], concerning their Kentucky lands., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 24 July 1797, from Meriwether Lewis, Shelbyville, [Kentucky], to Lucy Marks, stating that it has taken him longer than expected to settle their Kentucky land matters, but now he is heading to Georgia., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 2 July 1803, from Meriwether Lewis, Washington, D.C., to Lucy Marks, Charlottesville, informing her that he is heading west to prepare for his expedition and expressing concern for John Marks' education., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 31 March 1805, from Meriwether Lewis, at Fort Mandan, [present-day North Dakota], to Lucy Marks, Charlottesville, describing the expedition's journey to that point, including animals, plants, and geography., 4 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 21 April 1806, from Reuben Lewis, Three Forks of the Missouri, to Meriwether Lewis, Governor of the Louisiana Territory, discussing efforts to trap along the Columbia river and the difficulties of the fur trade company., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 29 November [1806?], from Reuben Lewis, at Colonel Hancock's near Fincastle [Kentucky?], to Mary G. Marks, Albemarle County, asking why she hasn't written and describing some of the people met on this trip., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 28 October 1807, from Meriwether Lewis, Albemarle County, to William Woods, Sr., Albemarle County, ordering a copy of his book for Woods., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 15 February 1808, from Meriwether Lewis, Louisville, [Kentucky], to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, describing his journey to Louisville, his efforts to settle Kentucky land claims, and his plans to head to St. Louis [Missouri]., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 1 December 1808, from Meriwether Lewis, St. Louis, [Missouri], to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, describing St. Louis, and informing her of his land purchases in and near the town, including a lot for her., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 12 October 1809, from [Jean Pierre] Choatear, Fort Mandan to Reuben Lewis stating he has heard of Lewis' appointment as a sub-agent for Indian affairs., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Letter, 5 January 1810, from William Meriwether, Richmond, [Virginia] to John Marks, Albemarle County, concerning the personal papers of Meriwether Lewis., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 28 September 1816, from Reuben Lewis, Fort Osage, to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, concerning his position as a Cherokee agent., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 3 April 1820, from Richard Searcy, Cadron [Arkansas?], to Reuben Lewis, Cherokee Agency, Arkansas River, concering business matters., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 10 June 1820, from S. Pleasonton, Treasury Department, to Reuben Lewis, Cherokee Agent at Arkansas, stating he has received Lewis' report on Cherokee depredations in Arkansas., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- Letter, 8 October 1829, from Alexander Pope, Land Office Cahaba, Alabama, to Reuben Lewis, Charlottesville, regarding a land warrant issued to Meriwether Lewis and assigned by Reuben Lewis to William Moore of Madison County, Alabama. Includes assignment from Lewis to Moore for 1600 acres., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 3 December 1835, from Thomas W. Gilmer, Charles Carter, Thomas W. Maury, David Anderson, and William Woods, all of Charlottesville, to Lucy Marks, Albemarle County, expressing their interest in producing a biography of Meriwether Lewis., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- Letter, 18 February 1841, from William Meriwether to Reuben Lewis, Albemarle County, sending transcripts of a letter, dated 21 June 1776, from William Lewis to Lucy Lewis [Marks] and a receipt, dated 17 July 1776, for rations., 2 leaves, negative photostats.
- advertisement, n.d., for John Hudson and Company of Lexington, [Kentucky?] listing merchandise., 1 leaf, negative photostat.
- List, n.d., of entries for persons for land warrants probably in Kentucky., 1 leaf, negative photostat.